Welcome back. Let's get back to
discussing all things data.
Earlier, we learned
about what data is,
its value to the project manager,
and the different types of
data a project
manager works with.
In this lesson,
we'll discuss how to
identify the most important
data for your project,
how to prioritize the
data you collect,
and how to effectively
gather priorities
from your stakeholders so that
you're meeting your goals.
Let's get started.
Did you know that
the average temperature for
most humans is 98.6 degrees?
So if your temperature reached
100.4 degrees
Fahrenheit or higher,
there would likely be signals
that something's not quite right,
like a sweaty forehead,
muscle aches, or
even dehydration.
Your brain would begin to receive
signals that something
is off because
it's the brain's job
to pay attention to
the signals that indicate there's
a problem threatening
your overall health.
That's how you should
think about data
when it comes to
managing your project.
There are all kinds
of information and
facts that you can gather
as a project manager,
but it's important for
you to be aware of
the signals that threaten
the overall success
of the project.
A signal is an observable change,
and it can help you to determine
the overall health
of your project and
identify early signs that
something isn't quite right.
Being aware of the
different types of data
you have access to
and knowing which
signals to respond to are key to
deciding what data
is most important.
Maybe you're asking yourself,
"How do I determine what data
is important?" Great question.
As a project manager,
it's up to you to look
for signals and to
prioritize data to
deliver positive results.
There are a couple of ways
you can begin to do this.
One way is to observe
your team's productivity
and output.
Identify which tasks contribute
most to the overall goal.
This will help you determine
the importance of
which data points—in
this case, tasks
and activities—you
should focus on.
Secondly, prioritize the data or
metrics that are most
valuable to stakeholders.
For example, let's say you
have an ongoing project at
a manufacturing
company to release
a portable home appliance
by the third quarter.
Your stakeholder
is concerned about
whether or not you'll
meet the deadline.
Okay, start by thinking, what data
do you have about the project?
You know that it's the
first quarter and you're
already $2,000 over budget.
But you also know
that you're 30 days
ahead of schedule according
to your burndown chart,
which measures time
against the amount of work
done and the amount
of work remaining.
You may think your project
is running as scheduled,
but there are additional
things to consider.
For one, the number of
tasks has increased
by ten percent over
the last three weeks
because your stakeholders
want to add more features
to the appliance.
And now your team's
productivity is
slowing down because
they're starting to
burn out from the late
nights and long hours
required to add in
those new features.
Now how do you feel about
meeting that third
quarter deadline?
Not so good, right?
What do you do?
You might be tempted to focus on
the signal that you're
$2,000 over budget,
but if your stakeholders
communicated that they're more
concerned with
meeting the deadline
than they were about
being over budget,
then you'll want to keep
an eye on key signals
related to time and scope
rather than budget,
and then hone in on
those signals to
identify and prioritize
areas to improve.
The relevant data
tells you you'll be
able to meet the
deadline, provided that
stakeholders stop requesting
new product features that
result in more tasks for
your team to complete.
You can use your productivity
metrics to forecast how you'll
manage an increase in scope
with your team's current
productivity rate
and communicate this
to your stakeholder.
To avoid having to
reset expectations with
stakeholders again and again,
you can keep your project
plan up to date with
the project's priorities
and ensure that
this information is
accessible to everyone.
Stakeholders can look to
your project plan for
a high-level overview of
answers to important questions,
success criteria,
artifacts, and the overall
health of your project.
Remember, there are a lot of
data points available to you.
Using signals,
focusing on the tasks
that have the biggest
impact on the project goal,
and aligning to your
stakeholders' priorities are a
good way to help you
prioritize the right tasks.
Now that you identified data and
prioritized it so that you're
working to meet business needs,
the next thing to
determine is how to
use the data to make
better decisions.
We'll cover that when we
connect in the next video.